Guide to the Shu Lea Cheang Papers MSS.381
Fales Library and Special Collections
Shu Lea Cheang Papers
1971-2024
1989-2002
Fales Library and Special Collections
Cheang, Shu Lea
MSS.381
28 Linear Feet in 4 record cartons, 25 manuscript boxes, 3 media boxes, 2 oversize flat boxes, 1 folder in a shared oversize flat box, 4 cassette boxes, 1 flat box, 1 flat-file folder, and 40 film canisters
22.57 Gigabytes in 22,304 computer files.
56 film reels
38 MiniDV
3 DAT
12 audiocassettes
24 Hi8
23 U-matic
15 VHS
26 Betacam_SP
5 Betacam
1 HDCAM
1 D-2
1 1_Inch_Video_Reel
Born in Taiwan in 1954, installation artist, filmmaker, and media activist Shu Lea Cheang received a BA in history from National Taiwan University in 1976 and an MA in Cinema Studies from New York University in 1979. She began her career in New York City as a member of the grassroots alternative media collectives Paper Tiger TV (from 1980 to 1990) and Deep Dish TV (from 1984 to 1990). She has since worked as a multimedia artist, creating internet-based participatory art installations and films critiquing political oppression, militarism, racism, heteronormativity, limits to freedom of expression, and also technological and environmental issues. In her career as a multimedia artist, her work has transitioned through the years from film and video to digital, to collaborating with web designers, technologists, writers and performance artists creating participatory works that enact cyber activism. The collection spans the years from 1971 to 2017, with the bulk of materials from 1989 to 2002. Although Cheang's collection documents most of her creations, the artworks and films prominently featured in this collection are Making News Making History: Live from Tiananmen Square (1989-1990); Color Schemes (1989); Those Fluttering Objects of Desire (1992); Fresh Kill (1994, restored in 2024); Bowling Alley (1995); Brandon (1998-1999); I.K.U. (2000); and Garlic=Richair (2002). The concept, design, execution, installation, promotion, and exhibition of these pieces are documented through paper and electronic formats, which include correspondence, project proposals, script drafts, notebooks, diagrams and sketches, photographic images, promotional material, reviews, press clippings, and research files. Edits and footage related to Cheang's films and installations are represented within the audiovisual material in a variety of formats.
Conditions Governing Access
Materials are open without restrictions.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Donated by Shu Lea Cheang, 2013; the accession number associated with this donation is 2013.381. In 2024, a restoration of Fresh Kill was added to the collection; the accession number for this accretion is 2024.025.
Appraisal
The following items were separated from the collection:
Two cartons of publications; extensive duplicate print material; financial material; tax documents; a Garlic=Richair project stamp; oversize movie posters; collected business cards; loose board game currency; oversize print of a Czech political figure; a Japanese fellowship certificate; 4 rolls of unused film negatives; a tin filled with painted fish; a tin filled with leaves and chrysalises; and an NYU diploma. Also, select mold and rodent-damaged paper materials were discarded as they were not original copies.
Video and photography equipment including AC adapters/camera chargers; several cameras (still and video); a remote control; AUX cables and other wires; a lightbulb, a mobile phone, ethernet cables; modem/lan and fax/mobile data cards; 5 phones and their associate cables from the Desire project.
Eight born-digital carriers were removed after forensic imaging and analysis determined items contained no usable data or were blank.
Two U-matic tapes and one VHS were removed due to mold infestation. Commercial audiovisual materials were removed: Dandy Dust; Ah! The Hopeful Pageantry of Bread and Puppet; Constance; ODË; You Don't Know Dick; and The Brandon Teena Story.
Arrangement
The collection has been arranged by an archivist, chronologically by art project date which is indicated in parenthesis after the title. Files found within each project title are arranged chronologically. Material not related to a specific project is listed chronologically before or after groups of project files.
Biographical Note
Born in Taiwan in 1954, installation artist, filmmaker, and media activist Shu Lea Cheang received a BA in history from National Taiwan University (1976) and an MA in Cinema Studies from New York University (1979). She began her career in New York City as a member of the grassroots alternative media collectives Paper Tiger TV (from 1980-1990) and Deep Dish TV (from 1984-1990).
Since the 1980s, Cheang has worked as a multimedia and new-media artist. Her internet-based participatory art installations and films address political oppression, militarism, racism, heteronormativity, freedom of expression, and also technological and environmental issues. She also drafts sci-fi narratives for her films and artworks, crafting her own "science" fiction genre of new queer cinema.
Cheang is regarded as a pioneering figure in internet-based art, with her multimedia approach using film, video, internet-based installation, software interaction and durational performance. She has collaborated with web designers, technologists, writers and performance artists to create participatory works that enact cyber activism. This cyber activism has involved the creation of progressive communities and awareness-raising around the recurring issues of power and desire.
The artist maintains a 21-acre estate in the Catskills Mountain region of Andes, New York, on which she grants groups of artists and farmers six-month residencies to farm and create art.
Audiovisual Access Policies and Procedures
Access to some audiovisual items in this collection is available through digitized access copies. Researchers may view an item's original container, but the media themselves are not available for playback because of preservation concerns. Materials that have already been digitized are noted in the collection's finding aid and can be requested in our reading room.
Audiovisual materials that have not been preserved may not be available to researchers. Materials not yet digitized will need to have access copies made before they can be used. To request an access copy, or if you are unsure if an item has been digitized, please contact special.collections@nyu.edu or 212-998-2596 with the collection name, collection number, and a description of the item(s) requested. A staff member will respond to you with further information.
Born-Digital Access Policies and Procedures
An access terminal for born-digital materials in the collection is available by appointment for reading room viewing and listening only. Researchers may view an item's original container and/or carrier, but the physical carriers themselves are not available for use because of preservation concerns.
Scope and Contents
The Shu Lea Cheang Papers (1971-2024) contains material related to artworks and films created by Shu Lea Cheang. The material in this collection not only represents one artist but also provides insight into the evolution of multimedia art at the turn of the 20th century when artists began to experiment more with combinations of film, digital, and web-based media. Art installation and film themes in Cheang's work center on political oppression, militarism, racism, heteronormativity, limits to freedom of expression, and technological and environmental issues.
The conception, design, execution, installation, promotion, and exhibition of Cheang's art installations and films are documented in this collection through paper and electronic files dating from 1971 to 2017, with the bulk of materials from 1989 to 2002. Files typically contain correspondence, project proposals, budgets, scripts and drafts, diagrams and sketches, photographic images in various formats, promotional material, and press clippings. Audiovisual material in this collection can be found on a variety of formats and includes recordings from early film producing projects; master edits and negatives of films; and videos used in art installations.
Cheang has generated a large body of work and this collection documents the majority of those artistic projects to some degree, but there are nine works with significant documentation in this collection. Her early work Making News Making History: Live from Tiananmen Square (1989-1990) is a collection of videos created during her two weeks in China, reviewing the media frenzy leading to the military action on June 4th, and similarly, her installation Will Be Televised: Video Documents from Asia (1990) is a series of five one-hour programs compiled from five regions in Asia, documenting camcorder users active in local struggles for press freedom and democracy. Color Schemes (1990) is an installation using the washing machine as a metaphor for the great American "melting pot" of ethnicity, presenting individuals from various ethnic backgrounds "representing" their ethnicity, creating a multi-layered discourse on racism and assimilation. Those Fluttering Objects of Desire (1993) recreates coin-operated pornography booths, with the concept behind it being the construction of desire in categorical ways, the form of the piece speaking to sexual desire as something that is constantly evading the viewer. Bowling Alley (1995) addresses power, access, and desire in public and private spaces within three separate installation sites and a web-based installation. Brandon (1998-1999) is a multifaceted web project that uses the nonlinear and participatory nature of the Internet as a means to explore and illuminate the story of Brandon Teena, a young transgender man, who was raped and murdered in Nebraska by two men when it was discovered that he was anatomically female. This project includes graphic surgery images in paper and electronic form in this collection. Garlic=Richair (2002) was an interactive online art project that imagined a post-capitalist society in the year 2030 in which community wireless would be the only internet and organic garlic the primary currency. Cheang's films Fresh Kill (1994, restored in 2024) revolves around two lesbian parents who are drawn into a corporate conspiracy involving the Fresh Kills Landfill and I.K.U. (2001) is self-described as a cyberporno.
Interspersed between these work files are Cheang's personal photographs; notebooks (1977 to 1997) containing ideas and plans for potential and existing projects; calendars and appointment books; 1977-1978 class papers from NYU; funding proposals and research; press clippings; written correspondence and emails; and recordings containing samples of multiple works most likely used for funding proposals and presentations. The collection contains Paper Tiger TV photographs of filming, notes, and video recordings of some episodes.
Art and society -- United States -- History -- 20th century.; Art museums -- Exhibitions.; Art -- Exhibitions -- 20th century; Art -- Exhibitions -- 21st century.; Digital art.; Installations (Art) -- United States.; Video art.; Politics in art.; Asian American artists.; Interactive art.; Interactive multimedia.; Racism -- United States.; Cultural pluralism -- United States; Short subjects; Race relations -- United States.; Women artists -- United States.; Art and the internet -- Exhibitions; Computer art.; Computer artists.; Transgender people -- Civil rights.; Transgender people -- United States; New media art.; Independent filmmakers -- United States.; filmmaking; Science fiction films.; Pornographic films.; Transgender people -- Identity; Photographs.; Slides (Photography); Screenplays; China -- History -- Tiananmen Square Incident, 1989; Korea (South) -- Politics and government -- 1988-2002; Korea (South) -- Social conditions -- 20th century; Taiwan -- Social conditions -- 1988-2000; Hong Kong (China) -- Social conditions.; Philippines -- Social conditions -- 1986-; Gender identity -- United States; Gender, sexuality & culture; film reels; Cheang, Shu Lea; Paper Tiger Television Collective (Firm); Teena, Brandon, 1972-1993; Walker Art Center
- Filming Stills -- Photographic Images, circa 1970s to 1980s (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Deep Dish TV -- Racism Research, 1971, 1981-1985, 1990 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- The Network Project -- Publications and Research, 1972-1973 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Notebook -- Notes, Ideas, 1977 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Daniel Hausman -- Photographs and Letter, 1977 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- NYU Cinema Studies -- Cheang Class Papers, 1977-1978 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Notebook -- Notes, Ideas, May-September 1978 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Photographic Images -- Cheang and Friends, 1979-1982, undated (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Letters, Scripts, and Notes, 1984-1986 (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Notebook -- Notes, Ideas, 1984, undated (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Walking or Riding on New York City Streets Film Footage, 1985; cuid28836 (Reel 381.0167)
- Paper Tiger TV -- Rereading "The Dragon", 1985 (Box 38, U-matic 381.0108)
  Existence and Location of Copies
  Two digitized versions of this recording are available for viewing through the finding aid for the Paper Tiger Television Archive (MSS 276): Rereading "The Dragon" - Master [Box 59, Media ID: 276.0096] and "Year of the Dragon" - Second Master [Box 59, Media ID: 276.0096]
- Cheng Tsun-Shing Letters, 1985-1986 (Box 2, Folder 1)
- Taiwanese Director Hou Hsiao-hsien -- Special Edition Movie Booklet, Press Clippings, Photographs, and Letter, 1985-1987 (Box 2, Folder 2-3)
- China Trip -- Correspondence, Scripts, Press Clippings, 1985-1989 (Box 2, Folder 4)
- Photographs -- Paper Tiger TV Filming, Cheang Portraits, and Cheang with Friends, 1985, undated (Box 2, Folder 5)
- Appointment Calendar, 1986 (Box 2, Folder 6)
- TV Generations Exhibition Catalog, 1986 (Box 17, Folder 2)
- In Search of the King of Songs -- Proposals, Budget, Correspondence, 1987-1989 (Box 2, Folder 7)
- In Search of the King of Songs -- Script -- 寻找歌王(分场大纲, 二稿) [Xun zhao ge wang (Breakout Outline, 2nd Draft)], circa 1987-1989 (Box 31, Folder 11)
- In Search of the King of Songs -- Script -- 寻找歌王 (分场大纲 ) [Xun zhao ge wang (Breakout Outline)], 1988 (Box 3, Folder 6)
- Research Files -- Charles Ogletree Writings, 1987-1998 (Box 2, Folder 8, Box 3, Folder 1)
- Appointment Calendar, 1988 (Box 3, Folder 3)
- Press Clippings, 1988 (Box 3, Folder 4)
- Notebook -- Notes, Ideas, 1988 (Box 3, Folder 5)
- Taiwan -- Writings, Press Clippings, 1988 (Box 3, Folder 7)
- Paper Tiger TV -- Video Festival Programs, 1988, 1991 (Box 3, Folder 8)
- Paper Tiger TV -- On Media Exhibition, 1989 (Box 3, Folder 9)
- The Trial of Tilted Arc (1989) -- Project Description and Press Clippings, 1985 (Box 3, Folder 10)
- The Trial of Tilted Arc (1989) -- Script, Press Clippings, Promotional Material, Correspondence, and Photographic Images, 1985-1991 (Box 4, Folder 1)
- The Trial of Tilted Arc (1989) -- Removal of Artwork Photograph (Box 17, Folder 1)
- The Trial of Tilted Arc (1989) -- Video Recording (Box 38, Video 381.0113)
- The Trial of Tilted Arc (1989) -- Exhibition Catalogs, Promotional Material, 1991 (Box 4, Folder 2)
- Art Publication, and Mapping the Terrain Symposium Booklet, 1989, 1991 (Box 4, Folder 3)
- The 90s -- Shu Lea Cheang in Chicago, Tape #1 -- Video Recording, 1989-07-27 (Box 7, Video 381.0033)
- The 90s Project, 1989 (Box 4, Folder 5)
- Color Schemes (1989) -- Whitney Museum Installation, 1986-1990 (Box 4, Folder 6)
- Color Schemes (1989) -- Photographic Images, 1987-1989 (Box 4, Folder 7)
- Color Schemes (1989) -- Exhibit Catalogs, Festival Programs (Box 4, Folder 8)
- Color Schemes (1989) -- Photographs (Box 4, Folder 9)
- Color Schemes (1989) -- WGBH New Television (Box 4, Folder 10)
- Color Schemes (1989) -- Video Recording, circa 1989 (Box 34, Video 381.0078)
- Color Schemes (1989) -- One Channel Version, 1989-1990 (Box 37, Video 381.0096, U-matic 381.0114)
- Color Schemes (1989) -- Exhibition Catalogs, Promotional Material, 1989-1990 (Box 5, Folder 1, Box 13)
- Color Schemes (1989) -- Reviews, 1989-1991 (Box 5, Folder 2)
- Color Schemes (1989) -- Photographic Images, 1990 (Box 5, Folder 3)
- Color Schemes (1989) -- Events, 1991-1992 (Box 5, Folder 4)
- Color Schemes (1989) -- Center of Contemporary Art, 1994 (Box 5, Folder 5)
- Color Schemes (1989) -- Filming and Working Photographs, undated (Box 31, Folder 7)
- China and Asia Notebook -- Notes, Ideas, 1989 (Box 5, Folder 6)
- Czechoslovakian Research Material -- Stavíme Stalinův Pomník [We Build Stalin's Monument] Game; 1968 Soviet Invasion Photographs Publication; Jan Palach Memorial Book; Art Prints; and Poster, 1989-1990, undated (Box 13, Folder 4-5)
- Making News/Making History: Live from Tiananmen Square (1989-1990) -- Press (Box 5, Folder 7)
- Making News/Making History: Live from Tiananmen Square (1989-1990) -- Press Clippings, Photographs, and Research Material (Box 5, Folder 8)
- Making News/Making History: Live from Tiananmen Square (1989-1990) -- Institute of Contemporary Art (Box 8, Folder 1)
- Making News/Making History: Live from Tiananmen Square (1989-1990) -- China Channel #1 -- Edit Master -- Student's Title, circa 1989-1990 (Box 38, U-matic 381.0110)
- Making News/Making History: Live from Tiananmen Square (1989-1990) -- 5 Channel Video Installation, Monitor 4: Channel 1 and Channel 2, circa 1989-1990 (Box 38, U-matic 381.0117)
- Making News/Making History: Live from Tiananmen Square (1989-1990) -- China / Channel 2 -- Student Video Submaster, circa 1989-1990 (Box 37, U-matic 381.0097)
- Making News/Making History: Live from Tiananmen Square (1989-1990) -- Channel 2 -- Edit Master, circa 1989-1990 (Box 38, U-matic 381.0116)
- Making News/Making History: Live from Tiananmen Square (1989-1990) -- Channel #3 Title Master, circa 1989-1990 (Box 38, U-matic 381.0111)
- Making News/Making History: Live from Tiananmen Square (1989-1990) -- China / Channel 4 -- Edit Master, circa 1989-1990 (Box 38, U-matic 381.0112)
- Making News/Making History: Live from Tiananmen Square (1989-1990) -- For Rick Bolton's "Revolution" -- Edit Master, circa 1989-1990 (Box 39, Video 381.0123)
- Making News/Making History: Live from Tiananmen Square (1989-1990) -- China Channel 5 Master, undated (Box 37, U-matic 381.0099)
- Making News/Making History: Live from Tiananmen Square (1989-1990) -- Hallwalls Contemporary Arts Center (Box 8, Folder 2)
- Making News/Making History: Live from Tiananmen Square (1989-1990) -- International Center of Photography (Box 8, Folder 3)
- Making News/Making History: Live from Tiananmen Square (1989-1990) -- Photographic Images (Box 8, Folder 4)
- Making News/Making History: Live from Tiananmen Square (1989-1990) -- Rick Bolton and The Revolution Will Be Televised Exhibition Installation, 1992-1993 (Box 8, Folder 5)
- Making News/Making History: Live from Tiananmen Square (1989-1990) -- Large Scale Photographs (5), undated; cuid5973; 1 item one box of photographs (Box 32, Item MSS.381.cuid5973)
  Photographs.
- For the Woman in You (1989) and Kill is Dutch for Stream (1991) -- Video Recording, 1989, 1991 (Box 39, Video 381.0152)
- Will Be Televised: Video Documents from Asia (1990) -- Information Packet, Script, and Notes, 1988-1990 (Box 8, Folder 6)
- Will Be Televised: Video Documents from Asia (1990) -- Proposal, 1989; cuid28839 (Box Electronic Records, E-records FA_MSS_381_ER_1)
- Will Be Televised: Video Documents from Asia (1990) -- China Research Material, 1989 (Box 8, Folder 7)
- Will Be Televised: Video Documents from Asia (1990) -- 5 Hours Compilation, 1989 (Box 8, Folder 8)
- Will Be Televised: Video Documents from Asia (1990) -- Expenses, 1989-1990 (Box 8, Folder 9)
- Will Be Televised: Video Documents from Asia (1990) -- Promotional Brochure (Box 8, Folder 10)
- Will Be Televised: Video Documents from Asia (1990) -- Contracts, Producers (Box 8, Folder 11-12)
- Will Be Televised: Video Documents from Asia (1990) -- Scripts, and American Film Institute (Box 8, Folder 13)
- Will Be Televised: Video Documents from Asia (1990) -- Philippines Edit Master, Final, circa 1990 (Box 34, Betacam 381.0082)
- Will Be Televised: Video Documents from Asia (1990) -- China / Presentiing River Elegy, Edit Master, circa 1990 (Box 34, Betacam 381.0083)
- Will Be Televised: Video Documents from Asia (1990) -- Taiwan, Edit Master, circa 1990 (Box 34, Betacam 381.0084)
- Will Be Televised: Video Documents from Asia (1990) -- Hong Kong, Edit Master, circa 1990 (Box 34, Betacam 381.0085)
- Will Be Televised: Video Documents from Asia (1990) -- Korea, Edit Master, circa 1990 (Box 34, Betacam 381.0086)
- Will Be Televised: Video Documents from Asia (1990) -- Sample Preview, Excerpts -- Master, circa 1990 (Box 38, U-matic 381.0115)
- Will Be Televised: Video Documents from Asia (1990) -- Review Press, Copy, 1990-1991 (Box 8, Folder 14)
- Will Be Televised: Video Documents from Asia (1990) -- Press Photographic Images, circa 1990-1992 (Box 9, Folder 1-2)
- Will Be Televised: Video Documents from Asia (1990) -- Pacific Campaign to Disarm the Seas Information and Letter, 1991 (Box 9, Folder 3)
- Will Be Televised: Video Documents from Asia (1990) -- Photographic Film Stills, Letters, and Promotional Material, 1991 (Box 9, Folder 4)
- China Footage, March 9, 1990; 381.0160 (Reel 381.0160, Reel 381.0161)
- Los Angeles Festival Program, 1990 (Box 17, Folder 3)
- How Was History Wounded: An Exclusive Report on Taiwanese Media (1990) Paper Tiger TV Exclusive Report -- Photographs, 1989 (Box 4, Folder 4)
- How Was History Wounded: An Exclusive Report on Taiwanese Media (1990) Paper Tiger TV Exclusive Report, with English Subtitles -- Master Edit, 1989-1990 (Box 34, Video 381.0088)
- How Was History Wounded: An Exclusive Report on Taiwanese Media (1990) Paper Tiger TV Exclusive Report -- 纸老虎电视 (Zhi lao hu dian shi = Paper Tiger TV); 独家现场报道 (Du jia xian chang bao dao = Exclusive live report); 历史如何成为伤口 (Li shi ru he cheng wei shang kou = How history is a wound), Hong Kong Master Edit, circa 1990 (Box 34, Video 381.0089)
- The Airwaves Project (1991) -- System Files, 1986-1987, 1992; cuid28841 (Box Electronic Records, E-records FA_MSS_381_ER_3)
- The Airwaves Project (1991) -- Script, Funding Applications, and Letters, 1986-1988 (Box 10, Folder 2)
- The Airwaves Project (1991) -- Capp Street Design, 1988, undated (Box 10, Folder 3)
- The Airwaves Project (1991) -- Wexner Center, 1990 (Box 10, Folder 4)
- The Airwaves Project (1991) -- Documents, Capp Street, SL Shoot on Video Recording, 1991-12-02 (Box 7, Video 381.0035, Box 11, Video 381.0044)
- The Airwaves Project (1991) -- Documentation / Joel Katz Shot, 1991-12-29 (Box 11, Video 381.0043)
- The Airwaves Project (1991) -- Workshop Documents (Box 10, Folder 7)
- The Airwaves Project (1991) -- Pamela 2 Sound Recording, circa 1991 (Box 7, Audiocassette 381.0025)
- The Airwaves Project (1991) -- Address Track / VITC, AMIC / The Airwaves Project, circa 1991 (Box 34, Video 381.0080 -- 381.0081)
- The Airwaves Project (1991) -- For Whom the Air Waves ITVS Proposal, 1991-1992 (Box 10, Folder 5)
- The Airwaves Project (1991) -- Montage 93 -- Audiovisual Transmission, 1991-1992 (Box 10, Folder 6)
- The Airwaves Project (1991) -- Financial Reports, 1992-1995; cuid28840 (Box Electronic Records, E-records FA_MSS_381_ER_2)
- Roundtable Discussion for Felix, 1991 (Box 10, Folder 8)
- Media Wars Then and Now Yamagata International Documentary Film Festival, 1991 (Box 10, Folder 9)
- Taiwanese Director Hou Hsiao-hsien -- Movie Special Edition Booklet, Press Clippings, Photographs, and Letter, 1991, undated (Box 27, Folder 7)
- Trans-Voices -- Proposals, 1991-1992 (Box 10, Folder 10)
- Gulf War / Network / Demo / 91; Abortion Rights / Holland Tunnel, 1991, 1993-07-02 (Box 11, Video 381.0045)
- Those Fluttering Objects of Desire (1992) -- Porno Joint Operations, Proposals, 1989-1991 (Box 10, Folder 11)